Guide to the Walter Beinecke Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Walter Beinecke papers
1900-2004
1930-1990
GEN MSS 846
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
21.47
(36 boxes)
The Walter Beinecke Papers consist of subject files containing correspondence, personal papers, autobiographical writings, and documents concerning the Beinecke family, the Sperry and Hutchinson Company, and Beinecke's business investments, book collecting, and work in Nantucket historic preservation; other correspondence, including correspondence with book vendor Howard S. Mott and family letters; other personal papers, such as financial and legal records, address books, and diaries; scrapbooks of clippings and other printed material; photographs, photograph albums, slides, and negatives relating to Beinecke's travels, the Beinecke family, and Nantucket; audiocassettes, videocassettes, and films, including interviews with Beinecke about Nantucket; and computer disks. Research strengths include the Beinecke family, the Sperry and Hutchinson Company, Beinecke's Barrie collection and other book collecting, and Beinecke's work in Nantucket investment and restoration.
Beinecke, Walter, Jr., 1918-2004
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Bridgette Beinecke, 2006-2008.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Boxes 10-11 and 36 (audiovisual material): Restricted fragile. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Box 28 (motion picture film and computer disks): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies of electronic files are available. Reference copies of motion picture film may be requested. For further information consult Access Services.
Boxes 33-34: Restricted until 2036. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Walter Beinecke (1918-2004)
Walter Beinecke, Jr., businessman and collector of J. M. Barrie books and manuscripts. Beinecke was a son of Walter Beinecke (Yale 1910) and a nephew of Edwin J. Beinecke (Yale 1907) and Frederick W. Beinecke (Yale 1909S), donors of the Beinecke Library building and endowment. His sister, Betsy Beinecke Shirley, was the donor of the Library's Shirley Collection of American Children's Literature. Walter Beinecke, Jr., worked in the tobacco and automobile industries, 1937-1948, and for the Sperry and Hutchinson Company, 1948-1963. In 1963, he founded the Osceola Operating Company and Sherburne Associates, through which he directed real estate investment and historic building restoration in Nantucket, Massachusetts, 1960s-1980s. Beinecke began collecting J. M. Barrie books and manuscripts in the 1930s, and donated his collection to the Beinecke Library in the 1960s.
Scope and Contents
The Walter Beinecke Papers consist of subject files containing correspondence, personal papers, autobiographical writings, and documents concerning the Beinecke family, the Sperry and Hutchinson Company, and Beinecke's business investments, book collecting, and work in Nantucket historic preservation; other correspondence, including correspondence with book vendor Howard S. Mott and family letters; other personal papers, such as financial and legal records, address books, and diaries; scrapbooks of clippings and other printed material; photographs, photograph albums, slides, and negatives relating to Beinecke's travels, the Beinecke family, and Nantucket; audiocassettes, videocassettes, and films, including interviews with Beinecke about Nantucket; and computer disks. Research strengths include the Beinecke family, the Sperry and Hutchinson Company, Beinecke's Barrie collection and other book collecting, and Beinecke's work in Nantucket investment and restoration.
Arrangement
Organized into two groupings: December 2006 Acquisition and March 2008 Acquisition.
Book collecting -- United States; Book collectors -- United States; Businessmen -- United States; Historic preservation -- Massachusetts -- Nantucket; Manuscripts -- Collectors and collecting -- United States; Real property -- Massachusetts -- Nantucket; Nantucket (Mass.); Audiotapes -- United States -- 20th Century; Audiovisual materials; Born digital; Diaries -- United States -- 20th Century; Electronic documents -- United States -- 20th Century; Interviews -- United States -- 20th Century; Motion pictures (visual works) -- United States -- 20th Century; Negatives (photographic) -- United States -- 20th Century; Photograph albums -- United States -- 20th Century; Photographs -- United States -- 20th Century; Scrapbooks -- United States -- 20th Century; Sound recordings -- United States -- 20th Century; Videotapes -- United States -- 20th Century; Book collectors -- United States -- 20th Century; Businessmen -- United States -- 20th Century; Barrie, J. M. (James Matthew), 1860-1937; Beinecke family; Beinecke, Walter, Jr., 1918-2004; Mott, Howard S., 1913-1995; Shirley, Betsy Beinecke; Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library; Sperry and Hutchinson Company
- December 2006 Acquisition, circa 1900-2004; 21.26; (34 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Folders are unarranged. Folder contents have not been verified.
  - Walter Beinecke Papers
    Conditions Governing Access
    Boxes 10 and 11 (audiovisual material): Restricted fragile. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
    - Admission control, 2 (Box 1)
    - Agendas, 2 (Box 1)
    - J. M. Barrie opening, 2004 (Box 1)
    - Beinecke family, 4 (Box 1)
    - Betsy Beinecke Shirley (Box 1)
    - Beinecke, Joy Anne (Box 1)
    - Boornazian (Box 1)
    - Collar, Ben (Box 1)
    - Libby Collar thesis (Box 1)
    - Dewey family, 3 (Box 1)
    - D general (Box 1)
    - Ex Libris (Box 1)
    - University of Florida Press, re: Lesser Antilles collection (Box 1)
    - Gaillard, Maia (Box 1)
    - H general (Box 1)
    - Hinrichs vs. Gifford (Box 1)
    - Hamilton College, 1990-2000; 6 (Box 1)
    - Interviews, 1977, 1981; 2 (Box 1)
    - K general (Box 2)
    - 9 Kimball Avenue. photograph album (Box 2)
    - Kinsella, William Sperry, 1998 (Box 2)
    - L general (Box 2)
    - Langley, William (Box 2)
    - My stories (Box 2)
    - Nantucket TV tapes (Box 2)
    - Newspaper articles (Box 2)
    - Reeves, Blair (Box 2)
    - Walter Beinecke: Catalyst for Change (Box 2)
    - Walter Beinecke III: Biological Technologies, 1998 (Box 2)
    - Walter Beinecke: personal bulky items, 3 (Box 2)
    - Walter Beinecke: personal correspondence; stories recorded by W. B., Jr., in 1997-1998 (Box 2)
    - Walter Beinecke: personal records, 2 (Box 2)
    - Walter Beineckes keepsakes, 3 (Box 2)
    - Walter Beinecke: photographs and photographs of portraits (Box 2)
    - Walter Beinecke III (Box 2)
    - World Monument Fund (Box 2)
    - Yankton College Talk (Box 2)
    - Appraisals and auctions, 5 (Box 3)
    - Beinecke family history, 2 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence with Yale University, 2 (Box 3)
    - Clippings, 4 (Box 3)
    - Historic preservation (Box 3)
    - Living will and instructions regarding death (Box 3)
    - Publicity and 1996 party (Box 3)
    - Other papers (Box 3)
    - Big B Ranch, 2 (Box 4)
    - Walter Beinecke personal files, 1900-1999, undated; 28 (Box 4)
      Scope and Contents
      Includes family photographs and albums, personal correspondence, and printed material
    - Ashley, Perry (Box 5)
    - Beinecke, Bernhard (Box 5)
    - Beinecke, E. J., 2 (Box 5)
    - Beinecke, Walter, Sr. (Box 5)
    - Beinecke biographical materials (Box 5)
    - Copy of "Frederick W. Beinecke: A Monograph" (Box 5)
    - East Africa (Box 5)
    - Fairview cemetery (Box 5)
    - Genealogical research (Box 5)
    - Kleberg, Robert, Jr., 2 (Box 5)
    - Ranch materials (Box 5)
    - Skyscrapers: Past, Present, and Future (Box 5)
    - Sperry and Hutchinson (Box 5)
    - Sperry and Hutchinson history, 3 (Box 5)
    - Sperry family (Box 5)
    - Stobart, John (Box 5)
    - Weickert, Alice Beinecke (Box 5)
    - Yale University trust agreement (Box 5)
    - Other papers (Box 5)
    - Amemiya, Tsuyoshi (Box 6)
    - Babbitt (Box 6)
    - Beinecke catalogue (Box 6)
    - Beinecke, Walter: real estate, 1992 (Box 6)
    - Caldwell, Mr. and Mrs. Henry Bryan, 1960-1975; 3 (Box 6)
    - Collection appraisals (Box 6)
    - Goldman Sachs (Box 6)
    - Lesser Antilles Collection, 1991-1997 (Box 6)
    - Mott, Howard S., 1950-1975; 6 (Box 6)
    - Short Hills Country Day School, 1960-1967; 2 (Box 6)
    - Trust draft, 2003 November (Box 6)
    - Trusts, 1990 (Box 6)
    - Yoakum residence, 1992-1994 (Box 6)
    - Bohlmann, Sharie Hatchett and Fanch (Françoise Ledan): lithographs (Box 7)
    - Family history, 6 (Box 7)
    - Financial (Box 7)
    - Joy Anne Beinecke memorial book (Box 7)
    - Joy Anne Beinecke photographs and memorials (Box 7)
    - New England Monthly, 1984 May (Box 7)
    - Nantucket photographs, 3 (Box 7)
    - Photographs, 4 (Box 7)
    - Silvan Incorporated (Box 7)
    - Collar, Barbara Beinecke: wedding album, 1994 (Box 7)
    - Slides: Peru and Ecuador, 1970 (Box 8)
    - Slides: Venice and Florence, 2 (Box 8)
    - Slides, 1959 July (Box 8)
    - Slides, 1961 June (Box 8)
    - Slides: Rainbow Springs (Box 8)
    - Slides, undated; 2 (Box 8)
    - Negatives, [1930s]; 23 (Box 8)
    - Negatives (continued), [1930s]; 2 (Box 9)
    - Negatives, 1938; 2 (Box 9)
    - Negatives (Box 9)
    - Audiocassettes, 6 audiocassettes in 4 folders (Box 10)
      Audiovisual material. Restricted fragile. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
      - Tape 1 of Walter Beinecke (1 of 2 audiocassettes), 1996 January 25; 1 (Box 10, Item barcode 39002104615753)
      - WB recording of paper for Literary Society Part II; Walter Beinecke Jr. practice presentation for the Monday Evening Club in Newburyport (2 of 2 audiocassettes), 1996 February 6-9; 1 (Box 10, Item barcode 39002104615761)
      - Walter Beinecke Jr. dictation: 8 letters to 4 people (1 of 2 audiocassettes), 1996; 1 (Box 10, Item barcode 39002104615779)
        Contents include: letters to G. Tobin re: Hamilton College, J. Short re: Bradford College re: pledge for 1996-1998, Stephanie ? re: Halprin June, Jean Weber - Nantucket Hist. Assoc.
      - W. Beinecke interview NTHP (2 of 2 audiocassettes), 1996 August 17; 1 (Box 10, Item barcode 39002104615787)
      - W. Beinecke - Correspondence, undated; 1 (Box 10, Item barcode 39002104615795)
      - "How the Rhinoceros Got His Skin" as read by Pop Pop, 1997; 1 (Box 10, Item barcode 39002104615803)
    - Videocassettes, 1993-2001; 17 videocassettes in 7 folders (Box 11)
      Includes "A Conversation with Walter Beinecke," "Dateline - 'The Whale'," "WB. Sr. films, 1924-26," Hamilton College commencement
      Restricted fragile material.
      - A Conversation with Walter Beinecke, NTV Channel 13, Nantucket Television, 1999; GENMSS846_0001; 1; 00:56:16 (Box 11, Item barcode 39002102300135)
      - A Conversation with Walter Beinecke, NTV Channel 22, Nantucket Television, 1999; GENMSS846_0002; 1; 00:56:03 (Box 11, Item barcode 39002102300143)
      - A Conversation with Walter Beinecke, NTV Channel 22, Nantucket Television, 1999 June 10; GENMSS846_0003; 1; 00:55:52 (Box 11, Item barcode 39002102300150)
      - Non-proftis dinner Jared Coffin House, 1992 January 17; GENMSS846_0004; 1; 00:43:33; This is a poor recording. The picture is not clear and the microphone did not pick up the people's voices. (Box 11, Item barcode 39002102300168)
      - Summer Memoirs, Preservation Institute: Nantucket 1999, GENMSS846_0005; 1; 00:12:05 (Box 11, Item barcode 39002102300176)
      - "Off Season" Copyright CPTV, 60 minutes, undated; GENMSS846_0006; 1; 01:00:16 (Box 11, Item barcode 39002102300184)
      - S&H Greenpoints, Broadcast Coverage, 2000; GENMSS846_0007; 1; 00:12:40 (Box 11, Item barcode 39002102300192)
        A list of contents included with the tape reads:
        1. In the Money - CNNFN
        2. Woman 2 Woman - KCBS-TV
        3. 2 News - WMAR-TV
        4. News 10 - WCAU-TV
        5. NBC 5 News at 5:00 - WMAQ-TV
        6. 7 News at 5:30 - WHDH-TV
        7. King Five News at Six-thirty - KING-TV
        8. CBS Market Watch - CBS
        9. Action News - WPVI-TV
        10. Eyewitness News - KYW-TV
        11. King Five Morning News - KING-TV
        12. News 2 Houston Daybreak at 5:00 - KPRC-TV
        13. Good Day Oregon - KPRC-TV
        14. News 4 at 9 - WRC-TV
      - Walter Beinecke, Sr. films 1924-1926, undated; GENMSS846_0008; 1; 01:24:16 (Box 11, Item barcode 39002102300200)
      - Dateline: The Whale recorded 2001 September 7, GENMSS846_0009; 1; 01:59:52 (Box 11, Item barcode 39002102300218)
      - Hamilton College Commencement, 132 minutes, 1993 May 23; GENMSS846_0010; 1; 02:12:15 (Box 11, Item barcode 39002102300226)
      - Cambridge College promotion video, undated; 1 (Box 11)
      - Legendary Resorts of the World box set, undated; 5 (Box 11)
    - Beinecke family history; map of the home of Walter Beinecke's parents (Box 12)
    - Cranford, New Jersey (Cranford Board of Trade, 1913) (Box 12)
      With notes about the Sperry family
    - Desk items, as of March 21, 2001 (Box 12)
    - Desk items, as of June 15, 2003, 5 (Box 12)
    - Nantucket: magazine articles, 4 (Box 12)
    - Clippings and correspondence (Box 12)
    - Photographs (Box 12)
    - Walter Beinecke, Jr.: archives (Box 12)
    - Other papers (Box 12)
    - Address book, 2002 (Box 13)
    - Big B Ranch, 4 (Box 13)
    - Condolence letters, 2004; 4 (Box 13)
    - Interview with Walter Beinecke, 1981 (Box 13)
    - Love expressed for Walter, 2000-2001; 4 (Box 13)
    - Photographs, 1930s, undated; 5 (Box 13)
    - Sam Proctor interviews, 1990 July; 2 (Box 13)
    - American Locker Group (Box 14)
    - Bankruptcy (Box 14)
    - GI Plastek, Inc., 1993-1996; 7 (Box 14)
    - Industrial General Corporation (Box 14)
    - PIN/Sherburne Swap (RH) (Box 14)
    - S/A Tree Program (Box 14)
    - Sherburne-Osceola (Box 14)
    - Stewardship (Box 14)
    - Walter Beinecke, Jr.: archives, 1973-1999 (Box 14)
    - Winthrop Publicity (Box 14)
    - Photograph album (PA 8) (Box 15)
    - Photograph album (SB 6), 1998 February 20 (Box 16)
    - Photograph album (SB 5), 1998 February 20 (Box 17)
    - Photograph album (PA 5) (Box 18)
    - Photograph album: Montana (PA 2) (Box 19)
    - Photograph album (SB 1) (Box 20 Oversize)
    - Photograph album (SB 2), 1964 (Box 21 Oversize)
    - Photograph album (SB 3), 1968-1973 (Box 22 Oversize)
    - Photograph album (SB 4) (Box 23 Oversize)
    - Photograph album (PA 3), 1989 (Box 24)
    - Photograph album: St. George and Germany (PA 1), 1934, 1936 (Box 25)
    - Photograph album (SB 7) (Box 26 Oversize)
    - Photograph (Box 27)
    - Printed ephemera (Box 27)
    - Clippings and photographs (Box 27)
    - Letters of Walter Beinecke, Jr., to Bridgette Durckel Schleicher (later Beinecke), 1991-1993 (Box 29)
    - Letters of Bridgette Durckel Schleicher, later Beinecke, to Walter Beinecke, Jr., 1990-2004 (Box 30)
    - Personal and family papers (Box 31)
    - Sperry and Hutchinson Company, circa 1999-2003 (Box 32)
  - Computer and AV Media
    Restricted fragile material. Reference copies of electronic files are available. Reference copies of motion picture film may be requested. For further information consult Access Services.
    - Unidentified 16 mm film reels, (2 reels) (Box 28)
    - Unidentified computer disks, (2 disks)
      - sh.tif 4/02, 2006-genm-3812-0001; 1 (Box 28)
        Restricted fragile material. Access copies of digital files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
      - [no label information], 2006-genm-3812-0002; 1 (Box 28)
  - Restricted Material
    - Restricted until 2036 (Box 33)
      Restricted until 2036. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
    - Restricted until 2036 (Box 34)
- March 2008 Acquisition, 1938-2004; 0.21; (1 box)
  Box 36 (audiovisual material): Restricted fragile. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - Commonwealth Bank (Box 35)
    Relating to Bernhard Beinecke
  - Crandell, Lou (Box 35)
  - Flannagan, Roy C. The Story of Lucky Strike. New York World's Fair edition, 1939 (Box 35)
  - Memorial service for Walter Beinecke, Jr, 2004 June 3; GENMSS846_0011; 1; 01:05:37 (Box 36)
  - Photographs (Box 35)